Juan Salazar

IT Manager

Nashville, TN 37013 (open to remote) • juan.fernando.salazar@gmail.com • 786-202-9099

https://www.linkedin.com/in/ferthelet • https://replit.com/@JuanFSalazar • Portfolio Website URL

SUMMARY

Experienced IT Systems Manager and Consultant with more than 15 years implementing, managing and supporting systems for sales, marketing, operations, finance, HR in industries such as insurance, cable TV, mobile operators, casino & hotel, government (statistics and judiciary), mining, and retail. Eager to move into devops and apply recent studies in Java Back End, Amazon AWS. Google Cloud

WORK EXPERIENCE US

IT Support Engineer

Nov 2019 - Jul 2022

Amazon, BNA15, 500 11th Ave North, Nashville, TN, https://www.amazon.com/

- Provided support for Fulfillment Centers business systems worldwide running on Windows, Linux
- Provided technical support for Kiosks/Lockers worldwide running on Linux, from root cause to final fix

IT Field Service Engineer

May 2019 - Nov 2019

Insequence Corporation, 750 Jim Parker Dr. Smyrna, TN, https://www.insequence.com/

- Installed the SDPro software in various car manufacturer plants to help them manage the logistics for car parts (.NET, Windows and SQL SQL Server based)
- Helped translate car manufacturers requirements into SDPro to align it with their assembly lines

Warehouse and Kitchen Help Associate

Sep 2017 - May 2019

- Amazon, BNA2, Lebanon, TN. In the process of applying to be Area Manager when I left the company.
- Cracker Barrel Restaurant, Mt Juliet, TN, diverse kitchen support roles (removing)

WORK EXPERIENCE ABROAD

Senior SW and IT Process Engineer

Oct 2015 - Nov 2016

National Institute of Statistics (INE), Santiago, Chile, https://www.ine.cl/

- Extensive use of frameworks to prepare the basis for an open tender to modernize the IT platform: TOGAF-OASIS
- Implemented Bizagi for business processes; Sitefinity for web content management and Moodle for eLearning management.
- Developed specifications for the new IT landscape for servers & consolidation, storage and for IT capacity planning

IT Manager

Aug 2012 - Aug 2015

Seminarium Internacional, Santiago, Chile, http://www.seminarium.com/

- Managed the whole IT infrastructure and services
- Implemented a project to migrate from Windows to Linux for 200 agents
- Managed implementation of CRM Salesforce for sales and marketing and Openbravo ERP for back office.
- Managed customer segmentations for marketing and sales campaigns and forecasts.
- Managed web site and database transfer to Amazon AWS.

IT Projects Management Intern

Jan 2011 - Feb 2021

German Agency for International Cooperation (GIZ), Bonn, Germany, https://www.giz.de/

- Full one-year scholarship awarded in public competition for a 1 year IT Project Management Certificate in https://www.bcw-weiterbildung.de/ including an intensive 6 month German language in https://www.goethe.de/
- Internship at Aurubis, the largest copper refinery in Germany. Delivered projects in Active Directory, email, IT capacity planning and monitoring for better visibility and systems uptime. https://www.aurubis.com/

IT Infrastructure and Systems Consultant

Jul 2010 - Jan 2011

Ausenco Ltd, Av. las Condes 11283, Las Condes, Santiago, Chile, https://ausenco.com/

- Managed the local area network(s), office and back office systems assisting local support IT Team
- Implemented network security with Watchguard and led migration from Exchange/Google to Office 365

IT Systems Lead Sep 2006 – Jan 2010

Enjoy Casino and Resort, Presidente Riesco 5711 Piso 15 Las Condes Santiago Chile, https://www.enjoy.cl/

- Managed operations and security for key corporate IT systems: Bally Software for slot machines management;
 Opera for hotel; Micros for restaurant and SAP ERP for the back office
- Designed and implemented SAP ERP own redundant Datacenter infrastructure and systems, managing SAP BASIS
- Managed implementation of Zimbra/Linux e-mail system for 4,000 users

Implemented IT processes according to CeBIT and ISO 27001 to address independent auditor reviews

IT Systems Consultant Apr 2005 – Dec 2005

Superior Court of Justice of Nuevo Leon, Monterrey, Mexico, https://www.pjenl.gob.mx/

- Implemented a new communications network, Windows Server 2003 and MS SQL Server for a mesh replication as per requirements of the "Virtual Court" project.
- Managed the Secure Internet Access project with redundant Bluecoat appliances and WhatsUp to monitor IT resources.
- Implemented MS Sharepoint as the document management system within the IT Division.

Systems and Sales Engineer Lead

Oct 2004 - Apr 2005

Teknos Chile (now Acanto), Santiago, Chile, https://www.acanto.io/

- Design, planification and implementation of a pilot remote call center for Banco Santander.
- Coordinated SAP ERP installation and operation. Assisted sales department with technical designs.

Lead IT SW ArchitectSmartcom PCS (now Claro Chile), Santiago, Chile, https://www.clarochile.cl/

- Jun 2002 Sep 2004
- Managed the integration of more than 100+ system software interfaces using IBM messaging MQ Series.
- Successfully managed the upgrade of 200 POS workstations nationwide to Windows 2000.
- Led the server and storage consolidation project for more than 100 servers with VMWare/Windows 2003.

Lead Systems Support

Aug 2000 - Jun 2002

SKY Chile TV (now DIRECTV), Santiago, Chile, https://www.directv.cl/

- Managed the operations, and customers plans and promotions on the Subscriber Management System (SMS), which including the billing, channels stock and information, alerts, and signal activation and deactivation
- Managed, monitored and assured excellent IT services and telephony SLA for IT and telephony services for a 80 seat 7x24 call center.
- Successfully managed the migration from Novell to a Windows Server platform

EDUCATION

Master in IT and Management (MTIG, 2 years)	Mar 2004 - Dec 2006
Universidad Catolica, Santiago, Chile, https://www.uc.cl/	
Informatics Engineering (1 year)	Mar 2003 - Dec 2003
Universidad Tecnologica Metropolitana, https://www.utem.cl/	
Engineer in Informatics Management (4 years)	Mar 1998 - Dec 2002
INACAP, Santiago, Chile, https://portales.inacap.cl/	
lava Baakand Davalanav (4 mantha)	Amr 2022 Com 2022
Java Backend Developer (6 months)	Apr 2022 - Sep 2022
Kenzie Academy from SNHU, Indianapolis, IN, https://kenzie.snhu.edu/	C 2010 F-1-2012
IT Projects Management Diploma (1+ year)	Sep 2010 - Feb 2012
AIT-BCW Advanced Training, Bonn-Essen-Hamburg, Germany, https://www.bcw-weiterbildung.de/	
IT Security Management Diploma (6 months)	Jul 2010 - Nov 2010
Universidad Austral, Argentina, https://www.austral.edu.ar/	
Quality Management and Organizational Development Diploma (1 year)	Mar 2010 - Dec 2010
Universidad de Chile, Santiago, https://www.uchile.cl/	
Strategy and Management Control Diploma (6 months)	Jul 2009 - Dec 2009
Universidad de Chile, Santiago, https://www.uchile.cl/	

TECHNICAL CERTIFICATIONS

Certified ITIL v3 Foundations Professional, AIT-BCW, Essen, Germany	Sep 2011
Protection of Innovation in Projects, Wirtschaftsclub Rhein-Main EV, Essen, Germany	Aug 2011
Incident Management in IT Security (Amparo Project), LACNIC-IDRC, Santiago	Oct 2010
Lead Auditor Information Security ISO 27001:2005, FCR-CGI Quality Corp, Santiago	Aug 2010
Lead Auditor Quality ISO 9001:2008, IRCA-RABQSA Quality Corp., Santiago	Jun 2010
Certified Information Security Auditor (CISA), ISACA Chile	Dec 2008
Certified Microsoft CRM 3 Professional (MS scholarship), New Horizons, Santiago, Chile	Feb 2007
Unified Communication, Ericsson, California, USA, https://www.ericsson.com/	Feb 2005
Microsoft Certified System Engineer (MCSE), UnO Educacion, Santiago, Chile	Ago 1999